Hi everyone and welcome to Upna College. today's
video, we about OOPS, Object Oriented Programming
Systems. We learn what classes and objects are
what the code we were in the main function
meant, along with inheritance, encapsulation,
polymorphism, and abstract concepts. We some
new keywords. Now, OOPS is important for two
reasons. First of modern programming languages
are on the concepts of So it's important how
OOPS works so we one language to another object-oriented
language, then concepts are clear from The second
reason is that in placements, the interviewer
us OOPS concepts. So it's important to those
concepts, how to apply them because sometimes
written, They will code to see that this concept
of and a code. This Java and C++. That's our
concepts should Now the class and you the notes
in the description box in which Java OOPS is
prescribed. If you C++ OOPS, then we have already
lecture notes in a separate video, so you can
go see that. We 15 concepts in 15 different
videos. In this video, we will cover the entire
OOPS! Let's start with the classes and objects
of Now, if talk about classes and objects,
then classes and objects were in programming
so that we real-world problems through coding
and programming. Now, we example of Maruti 800,
then Maruti 800, a blueprint must Then to the
factory, everything have set up And then all
the cars came according to the blueprint. So
if classes and objects, then every car Which
of Maruti's factory. And blueprint became our
class. So programming, all the entities That
entity can any object, can a person, it be
an animal. If we anything into world of then
we it an object. the instructions what properties
will what actions can an object what things
can all that blueprint is in a class. So this
is meaning of class and object. Now another
example of pen. Now we the example If we pens,
how we distinguish them? How will understand
We will understand differently to their color.
For one pen is red, one is blue, and one is
black. Now, these pens in Java code? We a class
and then some objects. Let's see how. First
of we to a public class in in every single
file. As soon the file name is oops.java, a
public class can called oops. Now, we the class
oops. Apart from let's we another class. And
this class Pen. So, Pen class. Now, we will
the blueprint of What is the properties of The
first property that  is its color. We have
defined string color. Apart from it its brand
or its type. So let's  a string in  which we
type. Now what can Either it a wall point pen
or it can a gel pen. So these two types.  Let's
it brand copy. So, we these two properties in
our blueprint to make a Apart from we a function
with Like the pen's job is to So, function will
perform writing. So, the functions, the methods
that we earlier, we are implementing here. So,
we some methods So, the that are defined we
them methods. So, we a function here. public
void system.out.println  writing. Something.
So, this way, we a class, i.e. blueprint of
the pen. In the blueprint have the color, the
type of and a function which the pen performs,
which is to write something. So, it writes
Now, we the blueprint. We only the blueprint.
We Maruti 800 and the showroom. Now, what will
is, we will objects. Now, we the objects We
are to in our main function. So our main function
comes in our public class. This is with and
this is our public class. Oops! We will our
main function public static void main which
takes a string of arguments in Now this main
function, we our first object of the pen. We
way like this. i.e. type will be class name
i.e. and we have is equal to new pen These are
the two parentheses So, we a pen Now, this
pen, to the color and type. So, let's that is
a blue pen and a gel pen. if we look then all
the properties, that we an object, now what
its property? What will Its color will be Its
type property. If we something else, it also
some properties. So how to access How to use
it? By So pen1.itsColor is equal to blue. In
this way, pen1, blue. And now if we to type
it, it is equal to gel. So this way, pen and
type Now suppose we want something We had used
by dot. Now how to call Means how to call this
this pen1? So to call we will have to dot So
what will happen We call it, pen1, so dot write.
Something like this. We the entire code, now
let's save it and run it to see what output
will produce. So the output that have that,
a has write something. What it First all, blue
colour was assigned to then its type was assigned,
then this write function was the help of and
after that this system.out.println line was
called. So this way, our classes and objects
work.  Every object has some properties and
methods. These properties are like color, type,
etc. are things associated with Along with
are methods. These are the data and members
Data and members are  stored in Data string,
int. And  members are  its functions.  Now if
we to the color and type then another method
in Public  void. Print, color.
And here we write this.color Now what this?
This is actually a keyword of Now this printColor
function will any object that And this will
this function which object has called this
Now we have taken only one color and one Now
let's create one more pen So we have which
we will newPen and this new pen we assign to
we have to pen 2 we type we give to it ballpoint
and now what we do is pen 1 and pen 2 we print
color so if we call print 1 for pen 1 so print
color is this the help of method will know which
object has called It has by pen1. Then printColor
will when printColor know that it pen2. That's
this tells us any method, in any scope, that
which object trying to access or Now this code
once. running, first thing is the pen 1, then
the pen 2. pen 1 is blue, pen 2 is black. So
we have read what objects, what are classes
and why this keyword is used in Java. Now another
example. This time we will the of a student.
So we will another class which we name as class
student. Now we to pay attention to whenever
we class, we the class keyword before So this
is the syntax of making which we in Java Second,
the names of that have already discussed start
with capital letters. By convention, the Java
start capital letters. functions start small
letters. So, class called student. What properties
can First of it have a name. Apart from we an
age. Now, this student class.
Let's to print this So public void print name.
this.name.
this.age.
StudentS1 is equal to new student. Now, if s1.name,
amen, and s1.age is equal to 24, now what we
is, s1.printinfo, we printed info, saved our
file, and we run it, now all the information
be So, we both the information printed. Now,
we make some changes again, same. Save and
run  So we have updated information printed
again. So we classes and objects in Now pay
attention to a small line. Here it is student
S1 is equal to new student. this line carefully.
Here new is a keyword which we have talked about.
As soon the new keyword, the memory heap. what
will happen Our whole object will be stored
there. So we according to the object. And here
the student and parenthesis, this keyword is
student  and parenthesis. Now if about parenthesis
is used where function comes. So this is a function
in This is special type of function which is
called constructors. Now constructors mean?
constructing something, making something.
Java, constructors is the objects of Now Java,
there are three types constructors. That we
three ways. The first type of constructors are
non-parameterized constructors. Those constructors
are those functions which do parameters. Now
let's its three properties before First of
all, the constructor of or a class will have
the same name as the class name. That the name
and the class name are the same. If we a student
class, then its name will student. Secondly,
constructors not return Constructions are functions,
but they return anything. Neither do any return
type. That means ink, string, float, all this
does not work on Neither does void work. No
return type written they objects.  And  third
property is that one object, constructor  can
once. Like normal functions, normal methods
can again and again  by We can normal functions
without again and But constructors are only
once. When  is When an object is Now the  first
type of constructor Now the first type of constructor,
the non-parameterized constructor. So how make
For example, if we to a constructor class, we
will first write student. Now, the return type
should but we write for the constructors. So
we student. After parameters do we have We
don't have to because it is non-parameterized
constructor. And here we any statement, like
we have here. constructor called. So, this way,
we a constructor. And whenever this object
is then this constructor will be called and
we will this statement printed. Let's run our
code. So, constructor called was printed first.
That means, whenever was the object was then
constructor called was printed. After rest of
code was run.  Now, if we think that the constructor
before, we deleted it, then also our code was
so how was running? So actually, Java, if we
don't any non-parameterized constructor in the
class, then Java automatically default. So
this constructor was Java itself, but now we
our own, then Java called Now, second type
of constructor, that is parameterized constructor.
Now, if  we start parameters in is, we a name
and an age here.  So, we initialize by By these
two statements from we  write this.name is
equal to name.  This.name here is the name And
this name is the parameter that has That's
there a difference.  Along with if we this.age,
we can this equal to age. Here this.age is
the age and this is the of our argument which
the constructor So here name and age have Now
whenever we create here we to name and age in
So we pass and amenAge 24. And after print
information.  we we get name and then the age.
So what did see? parameterized constructor.
And then what did do? It assigned And finally,
we the information printed from the function.
Now third type of constructors are copy constructors.
This concept has There are copy constructors
which by default. user also be defined. But
all the copy constructors It user-defined.
copy constructor is to an object and another
object. For example, if we had not got name
and age in we would got another student. The
second student, whom we have named S2. Now,
student came S2 and what did is, we the S2.name
And this.age, S2.age. We this constructor copy
constructor. Because it student2 and its current
object. Let's try it once. student1 because
we that constructor. S1.name as Aman. S1.age
as 24. Now we another student. Student S2.
New student. Now we will pass our uh S1 and
the information  If we copy constructor, then
we have this call sufficient before If we copy
constructor, we this constructor as because
it by default. So student, we simple empty constructor.
Now if save it and run it, then we have Amman
and 24 And we the code carefully, we never the
properties We um directly assigned S1's properties
to S2. So, we to a copy of  we make a constructor
in pass the object inside and it copies all
the properties. So,  all these were our concepts
related to objects in classes. Along with this,
we studied and studied what constructors are.
Now we will study the different concepts  There
are four major concepts in First, abstraction,
encapsulation, then inheritance and then polymorphism.
We these four concepts carefully. We any object-oriented
language. These four concepts are included
in Once we these four concepts, then whether
we Java to C++ or C++ to Java, things will
very easy The way the world is so Java. Meaning,
there be a mechanism to that Like there constructors,
there destructors as Because programmers are
very smart. And in C++, like we constructors,
we another function called destructor. But Java,
this mechanism is automatic. That we destructor.
There is an automatic garbage collector What
garbage collector do? It the object being the
variable that not being used, the memory that
is So it intelligently whether the object is
being or and it is in it automatically deletes
it. That's we to destructors That's Java is
an efficient language and it work very little.
So whenever someone asks you how to destructors
in then you destructors because Java has garbage
collector. The concept we going to is called
polymorphism. Polymorphism of two words. poly
and morphism poly means many, very much morphism
means forms when we one work in different ways
in then we call it polymorphism now there are
two types polymorphism first is function overloading
second is function overriding first type is
run-time polymorphism first type is compile-time
polymorphism second type is run-time polymorphism
here we compile-time polymorphism  When of inheritance
in this video, we will later. Compiled time
polymorphism  means function overloading. In
simple language, means that different functions
but they have  the same name. It  that functions
are different things but their names are the
Now their names the same? We will it better
um if  Now we had already created a student
class. We two properties in Now let's we to
a function public void print info. Now this
print info function. Let's assume we to only
name in So we passed and we wrote it. Print
name. Now another function public void with
print info.  and we pass the And this function,
we have  print the student's And a third function.
public void print info string name int age
And here we both things, i.e.  name. plus our
age. Now we these three functions in the same
class and these three functions is same. This
thing, this implementation in Java or even
C++ is called polymorphism. That means we the
same function for different purposes. Now what
the benefit of That we someObject.printInfo
and only the information that to print in So
automatically it see which function it that
information. For if we already a student S1
and we need print its age for So call print
info and pass the age of And save it and run
it, then what output? We get 24. Similarly,
let's that we to print
Let's call it again. After we have our name
and age. So, similar way, different functions,
when they the same name, Java, this concept
is called function overloading. Overloading
means creating the same name functions in the
same class. Now, it's not like we write here
public void print info string name and public
void print info string class. There some rules
that have follow to overloading. First of there
should be differentiating factor in these functions.
Either the return type should If we to string
name and string name then one return type be
void, then the return type be void. Second thing,
if their return type same, the parameters should
different. If is a string type argument in then
there should be an integer, float, or boolean
in If this also the same, then there different
number of arguments in That is, if we given
a public void print info string name then if
we a public void print info string name then
we to another argument. Otherwise, an error.
If we the intage then there will in our code.
That's it's Compiled Time Polymorphism. Compiled
Time Polymorphism means when the compilation
of our code on, it detects that there problem.
That have we polymorphism properly? In run-time
polymorphism, the compiler can't find any errors
If we make here, then errors will What run-time
polymorphism? When the code runs, then errors
will Which is more dangerous. Because if we
we made a big app from now coders, programmers
can run and see if there any problem in that
can But if that app goes into production once,
the users, and there are in runtime, and problems
in then that is a big problem. Because a lot
of users are impacted. That is we should to
polymorphism, so we compile time more and runtime
a little less. But both are because placements
and both concepts should Now the next concept
we will talk about is called inheritance. In
English, means to one generation to the next.
And Java, classes and objects, it means to
the one class when someone other class. means
it all properties, then we call as inheritance.
For example, we made a class. We named Shape.
Now this is Shape class and it has another
property called Color. We a shape and give it
a color. Now if different shapes. So rectangle
is triangle is different, circle is different.
These different shapes with different sizes.
They have different area calculations, perimeter
calculations. That's these can't in this shape
class. So for we to class separately. So let's
make a class separately, triangle. So what
write in Extends  shape. So what happened Triangle
class has extended, inherited.  We the properties
of Shape class. Now, the triangle class, there
will be a property even if we that property
inside Let's the example. this, let's create
We create an object triangle type.
Now, if we colour for suppose we colour to red.
So, what happened No error came. That means
T1 already a colour existing in which we assigned
Whereas, we define So, is called a class property
score. Not properties, but methods. When the
class inherits, that process is called inheritance.
Now, there can be many uses For the example
of there can be many buttons on Now, we always
have of in an extended round rectangle. So,
what we will do is, we will define the shape
After the classes with different buttons will
inherit it. So, the re-usability increases.
Re-usability means we to the same code again
and We the same code in all classes. The class
from the properties are is called the base class.
And the class the properties is called the
subclass or child class. And base class is called
the parent class. So, inheritance works this.
There are 4 types There are 5 types C++ has
multiple inheritance which is Java classes
but Java is smart language so it interfaces.
Now if about inheritance, there are 4 types
of The first one is single level inheritance.
Single level inheritance means there will a
base class above and a derived class and a single
level of inheritance will So let's an example
of First of a class named Shape.  Shape class,
we some of characteristics or some function.
So,  we a function. Public void area. this
function do? The function's job is to display
So, it displays area. Now, let's another class.
So, this class Triangle.  Triangle is type
of shape. So, we can say that whatever properties
are they will automatically in the triangle.
Along with that, there be additional properties
So, let's a class here, triangle. Now, this
triangle class has the shape class. That too,
single-level inheritance. And inheritance,
we a keyword in which we call extends. So we
will write class triangle extends. Which class
is being extended? What our base class? Our
base class is shape. So syntax is something
like this. First we write derived class, then
write extends keyword, then we our base class.
So this way, all the properties of will our
triangle class. Now all the properties will
but we will learn thing when axis modifiers.
But now let's that all the properties are there.
So the triangle class, we again create an area
function. And this area function? First of
the parameters. a triangle, we will the  length
and  its height.  And we will write half into
length into height. This is our triangle's area.
So, type of inheritance is called single-level
inheritance. level below the inheritance. Now,
there is another type of inheritance. The second
type is multi-level inheritance. Multi-level
means one level. Now, have a shape here. The
triangle has extended Now, another class which
is called equilateral triangle. Now equilateral
triangle will be triangle. Equilateral triangle
is a triangle whose sides are equal. The properties
of will equilateral triangle by That's equilateral
triangle will derived class And in this equilateral
triangle, we can another function. Let's we
the same function again. We the  same parameters
again. Length is our height. And inside we
be our area.  So this way, multiple levels
have Basically two levels have The first base
class was our shape. A triangle  An equilateral
triangle This is we have chained inheritance,
which is called multi-level inheritance. The
third type of inheritance is hierarchical inheritance.
Hierarchical inheritance means that there only
one base class and multiple derived classes
have the same base class. For example, we an
example here, the shape is inherited by the
triangle class. Now another class, which we
call circle. Let's the shape class and make
an area which the area. Now the circle area
is very easy, we know it. Bye. Odd. So in this
way, the triangle class is also shaped class.
The the circle class is also a shaped class.
That's this type of inheritance is called hierarchical
inheritance. A hierarchy is formed. First comes
our base class. Then comes our different derived
classes. fourth type of inheritance in Java
is called a hybrid inheritance. In we different
types of inheritance in same place. any branch,
we single inheritance, multi-level inheritance,
or hierarchical inheritance. There is a fifth
type of inheritance called multiple inheritance.
Multiple inheritance is in Java, is C++. In
Java, we use to implement We will see how it
is Here we our inheritance. The next topic we
will about is Encapsulation. Before encapsulation,
we two things. What are our packages in Java
and what our access modifiers. First of let's
about packages. If a package, we know is a in
English. A is that a carting and put related
items in Meaning the same items. Like you a
package of pens, erasers, pencils. Similarly,
things have logically Logically, things shouldn't
be this because we thousands of lines code
whenever we big companies. And if a new person
team, he the same code, so becomes difficult
to things We also forget what code wrote so
code very well so that the meaning. Now, way
to good format is to packages in Java. We related
code For we an example, if we about a website,
there be a lot of things in There can one thing
that only buttons. There can thing that only
color Or its look is to handled. There can thing
that the user's data. Now these three different
parts of a website. So them, if we to any inbuilt
functions, then what do? all properties.
Make the properties of Along with that, user's
data needs to be modified, deleted, added,
all the things will functional. Make separate
package for So way, different packages functions.
Now Java, there are two types of packages in
First, those that already exist which we call
built-in packages. Second, those that the user.
That we can our own packages. Now if talk about
built-in packages, we might not have realized
it, but we lot of Java packages so For example,
if we want to some input in then we the Scanner
class. To the class, we to a statement on import
java.util.star After we the scanner class. actually,
this java.util is a package in Which already
lot of related classes, utility classes, utility
functions, which we can directly use. There
are many more like linked list, data structures,
stacks, queues, hash maps, linked hash maps,
trees, we classes and packages at time. So there
are packages like and this package is basically
related items, you them together so that you
make that you make logic of First, we will
create a new file for We will as Bank. We will
name Public Class Bank. Now, we will store
this of Bank.java. Now, a new folder. this folder
Bank and this file there. First all, the package
as Bank. We have it. and put it the folder So
here we our package and our Bank Class. Now
this Bank Class, we all information related
which there may be our employees, accounts
created, etc. So first of let's a class, which
we account. Now this account class, will store
some basic information. which, our string name
public and import the oops class. a we to import
it first. importing, we will write bank. So,
we the bank name package. And we will use We
will write here bank.account. We will account1
of new bank.account. and we account1 for the
account is for our customer1 so this way we
can the other package in our package and our
package in the other package Now before moving
ahead, let's about something access modifiers
Access modifiers are four types three types
Access Modifiers means defining what will accessible
to We  have a of resources. A class stores a
lot of information. Some  information sensitive
like our passwords which we to all files. Let's
there  is big system of company in the accounts
department is There are functionalities software
for The tech team is also working. There are
some software for too. Along with we have some
software Now  we don't want the accounts team,
which are business transactions of or the internal
transactions of of company, by  our tech team
or our management team. In same way, the sensitive
information that which file should And these
different types information in Java four types,
which are  our public, private, protected,
and um For  example, we have a public string
name. Now, if we our main function in public
static void main. this function, then our main
function is also public. Why it necessary Because
when the compiler works in Java runtime environment,
then we have find which class to start execution
That's  we main class as private protected.
We to public so that accessible. Now, we Now,
we an account in Account 1. account 1, we made
a new account. So, new object. Now, account
1. So, named it Apna College. So, what happened
We our public name here in our main function.
Now the type of access modifier is default.
Now we have by Now we have to specify by Default
already exists. That means of any parameter,
any property, of any function, if you don't
apply then it default type. Default type means
that within its package. Only another package
will to access i.e. we put the name of in only
those packages will our default. Now if we
public from then the name will be our default
type. Now third type of access modifier we
is protected. Protected means that in its package.
Along with if to another package, then only
subclasses. The rest cannot access. i.e. if
we protected here, and then write a string
email. So this email information can the second
package by all classes and anyone can here
we account 1, for we write email.
4th type of access modifier is private. private
outside the class. can within means, if anything
private then only the account class can it.
Neither its subclasses will nor any other class
will it, nor any other package will be allowed
it. That means, bank class can't of account
class. For we create a string password So here
if we try to account1, ABCD, then it  possible.
Here the error came, the field account password
is not visible. That means this bank class,
account class, like its password is visible,
you reset Now question, then private things?
So for them, there is a concept of getters and
setters  So whenever something private, we
two types functions in The first type of function
is called getters. Getters means that  private
thing. And other type of functions are setters.
Meaning that private thing. So this way, directly
that private thing. Instead, we a function for
Meaning what have to do is if we get we a function
for Public string  get password. the get password,
We will return this.password. And this.password
is returned. So this is our getter. Now we also
a setter. In some cases, the password by and
we a setter for So let's do setPassword here.
Let's a string named pass. And this.password
with string pass. Let's make it public void
because it return So we made this getter. We
have made this as a setter. Now, we will do
is first all the password. So, in the set password.
Our password is abcd. And after that, we print
it. So, account1.getPassword. So, getPassword.
If we save this and run it, then our account1
password And us, output is abcd. So, this way,
private functions. If we want to, we the option
to the user. The password is set. Now, it can't
be set So, can remove completely. it private.
If we the function private, then we won't from
the bank class. You will think what is use of
It used to call a set password automatically
and a random password. So, the set password
cannot by this class. But our getPassword function
can So, many OOP concepts can in to real world
problems. we have read packages and access
modifiers. Now let's talk about what encapsulation
meant. So indirectly we encapsulation. Encapsulation
means Desi language that you data and its functions
in one entity. That whenever you a class, then
you do data and its functions. Data means the
properties of Functions means the methods We
and one eh unit.  We this unit Java. Now, we
call  thing Encapsulation. Encapsulation English
means encapsulating So, we the data and its
functions,  properties and methods in one
unit. So, classes and objects means is encapsulation.
With the encapsulation,  data hiding is possible
in Java. Data hiding means you some data that
you want user, the sensitive data. So how do
we implement the access modifiers. We which
data private, protected, public, and how it
be hidden. Apart from fourth main pillar of
OOPS is Java, which we call abstraction. Abstraction
means important things  Showing and non-important
things from oh abstraction and data hiding.
We  will after abstraction that what is the
difference between Abstraction means showing
important things and useless things from Now,
oh abstraction in Java in two ways. First,
you use the abstract keyword to abstract classes,
functions, properties.  Second is to interfaces.
First we will discuss what is abstract class
and what is abstraction.  We our original class
oops and save it. This is our class  and we
will abstraction. Now let's we want to an animal.
animal, first we a blueprint. After we different
types of animals.   Now, different types of
animals, uh we understand that a class  is its
base class in inheritance. And the blueprint
is its class. So first, let's an animal's blueprint
and  different animals. Now, a class called
Animal. There be some functions in first function
is Public Void Walk.  So, the can We have
a function Now,  animal class will a new class.
We name that Horse. So, what the Horse class
do? extends the animal. In which we the walk
function again. Public void walk.  And we display
Walks on four legs. Now, another class.  We
call it chicken.  Chicken is also an animal.
Extends. Animal. Public void walk.  We display
in Walks on two legs. far I remember. So now
we two classes. Horse class and chicken class.
Both classes extend And we have  made a walk
function  Now question is that whenever we a
horse or chicken, do we in the animal class?
Because all the properties of are directly the
horse class chicken class. So can we there
and see if the user has the right to and walk
So here, a way, the animal class is irrelevant.
We don't need And we won't an object anyway.
Why? Because an animal is a specific animal
that we an object of. We can new horse from
We can new chicken from There is no type So
we need to So this class abstract. Abstract
class. How the abstract class? We wrote the
keyword abstract Abstract means English language
that there is a concept. There is a thought,
a blueprint. It doesn't have It just exists.
We can We can create But we actually use So,
class is also like that. We it a concept that
there must There must be 3-4 things in But
the actual animals that will be horse and a
chicken. It's not an it's just a concept. This
is we made it abstract. And now the abstract
class, we can make some properties, some functions
abstract. For this walk function has function.
This function only exists. Now we  want that
whatever animal class we it walk function  because
all animals can  That's we this walk function
but it no use. We can this function abstract.
And here we abstract void walk. And this function
abstract, then we its implementation. We putting
a semicolon here. There will be a function
called that every type animal. So if we a horse
and chicken then there be a function called
in So this is abstract class. Now when we the
animal, we have a walk, chicken. Now in  the
main class? a  horse type horse. And that we
will call .walk. We will save it and run it
So our output we will have walks on four legs.
So is  how abstraction is How done? Oops! Inside
or whenever we an object.  So here if we animal
type, animal animal is equal to new animal.
So what happened Let's walk for Let's  save
it run it. So as soon we animal, there an error
here that cannot instantiate the type animal.
Here, instantiate means to initiate, create.
Here, an animal type object. Why can't make
it? Because animal is an abstract concept.
It's concept, it's a blueprint. It can't actually
be created. And the type of error we here is
called runtime error. There no red line When
it was run, the error came. So that runtime
error. That's why if we... If we some concepts
incorrectly, then we can't detect When they
need to on runtime, then we can detect them.
That's we OOPS concepts very well. Now let's
some properties of our abstract class. The first
property is that the class must be declared
with abstract keyword. It can both abstract
and non-abstract methods. Here we made If we
wanted, we normal method without the abstract.
Public void eats. print animal eats. We have
made a function by doing animal eats. We can
call eat for Horse doesn't have eat function
but it has inherited all properties. It can
So, we can print first walks on four legs then
eats. Third thing is it cannot be instantiated,
it can have constructors and static methods
also. If we cross the constructor, we create
a constructor here. If we create a constructor
for we can in you are creating a new animal.
Let's save this. And if these two here, if
we a constructor of horse inside we will write
created a horse. What do We animal in the animal
class, a horse in the horse class. And now this
code. the main function, carefully what we
a horse. So, as soon we created first we wrote
you are creating a new animal, then we created
a horse. So what find First all, call was made
the animal constructor, then call was the horse
constructor. That whenever you of derived class,
the base class constructor is then the derived
class constructor is This concept is called
constructor chaining in that is, the of constructors
runs whenever you in inheritance. After that,
talk, it can have final methods which will
force the subclass not to change the body of
the method.  There some functions that finalized,
which if you want, you all the functions in
way. For if we  Herbivores, we in Eats that
Herbivores, the animals, will all the plants,
you can't change So, kinds of concepts  keep
Now, let's talk about the second type of abstraction
that uses interfaces. Interfaces have pure
abstraction.  Here we have added the function
which can use and chicken. And this function
is not abstract, still Java has it. So this
not pure abstraction. Pure abstraction will
all useless information and all useful information
for the user. So this pure abstraction comes
in with the help Interfaces are only some of
fixed properties. Let's define with the interface
keyword. We'll interface and then write whatever
name want to we animal name. Now in this interface
animal, what to is to a walk function. We'll
write void. Walk. So our whole animal is defined.
Now here we want to the animal constructor.
So that possible, we error in because the constructors
cannot there. Now if we to create a voidEat
here. So we error because there should be no
non-abstract function There be implementation
of So we cannot implement the property of will
the specific animal. That means if we class
Horse And we don't extend here, we the interfaces
in So we'll the keyword implements, animal.
And we've implemented so all its properties
are there. So now what have do is, the walk
function again. Here we've defined it, and
we implement it So we'll void walk. Walks on
four legs. Here we public, here also we public.
So here we call Walk. Let's recap. We animal
interface. We made an abstract function Then
the horse implemented the animal and it implemented
Implemented means used. Now let's some of properties
Interfaces are which all the fields are Meaning,
whatever variables we define, they  by default
public, static and final. m Public, static and
final. If  we want to the number of  we  fixed
number of eyes. The  properties for will all
animals.  We can't change So, static  for all
animals. It will the value will fixed and it
public. It everyone will accessible. The second
property is methods are public and abstract
by default. We this method void. Even we public
from this method is by default abstract and
public There an abstract keyword in public
keyword either. But when we implement then we
a public keyword in If we this public keyword
from here, then there will be error. The error
will because if public not written of the walk,
then by default access modifier will default.
But we should have public. This is by default
public because it is an interface. Now we about
inheritance, we multiple inheritance. Multiple
inheritance means two base classes and one single
derived class is used by Now it is not possible
in Java classes but can How? If we an interface
animal and another interface which we Herbivore.
So this interface we can implement the animal
in the horse. and also implement because the
horse is an animal and also herbivore that only
plants. this way, both classes at This is called
multiple inheritance, which Java with classes,
with interfaces. This often interviews. That's
why we emphasis on That's why we should it.
Now we many concepts. Let's last thing, small
thing, which is called static. We static keyword
in again and Especially when we main function.
We main function as public static void main.
Now we main, void and public. What static mean
in There is a special keyword in Static means
the thing that accessible like We tell to those
properties which are common Like... If we an
example of a class,  let's we make student.
So the class, we will  define its string, some
name, then we will its school name. Now we
every  student? No. We the entire student class.
So that, we will make it static.  So as soon
as we the school static, means all the objects
in will have same name for Let's how we the
main function. First, we student.school. now,
we the student class first, then to access
things by But the things we static, static methods,
static variables, we can access them That means
we student.school here as jmv. So if error,
we directly access static things because they
class objects. Objects are private objects like
the name. The static is for all objects. Now
student.school. Let's a student too. Student1
is equal to new student. student1, we write
the Suppose we wrote Tony. So we wrote this.
So student1. But we it school because it is
static. for that, student.school. But here we
also print for student1. school. If and run
it, then what will be Student1's school. Which
is JMV. But if suppose the school name changes
So school name changes, suppose of JMV, if it
becomes After that, all the students. So, static
is made for those properties that we want to
common. Now, if we school name separately,
store then what we have to do? every student.
Here, we update Some these functions can also
static, which the class, which we call Like
public static void change school. So, all the
students, if we change So, here can do school
is equal to new school. So, the has automatically
detected that the school we talking about is
our static school. We it new school. So, this
way, the static variable will changed Now, static
keyword in Java Either we it of like we have
it Or we it of functions. Or we it of blocks.
That if we a block static, then how should
it? or we can in nested classes. Now, static
keyword in memory is all the things that are
static in given memory only once and the objects
are given to memory again and again. That's
whenever we to save memory and we have common
information, we that variable, that function
static. So, this way, we all the concepts of
oops in Java. All these concepts are important
because they are used whenever you your internship
or Java to a project or even switching you
have done this, you will web development, app
development, some other language C++, will
use Or if you to good code then you should know
how to organize OOFs is things systematically,
some good concepts so that our can be better.
We can create system in the code by in That's
we the OOPS concept. Along with we lot of questions
in many rounds, our OOPS knowledge is checked
very well. If we C++, then C++ and Java's OOPS
concepts overlap. So if you Java or C++. You
have half of the same concepts. Now some extra
things according to the language. So I hope
that today's class. Apart from you any other
video, you can comment below. today. next video.
Till then keep learning and keep practicing.